Guide to the New-York Historical Society Original Building Planning & Construction Records 1848-1946 NYHS-RG 3
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series III. Central Park West Construction: Central Portion, 1880-1918; 14.43 Linear feet in 7 document boxes, one artifact box, 23 oversize folders, and one roll of drawings
  - Other Expenditures, 1894, 1900, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Includes building-related expenses not paid from the Building Fund.
  - Building Committee Minutes and Trustees of the New Building Minutes, 1901 June 5-1907 October 15 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Building Committee. General (1 of 2), 1901-1903 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    This folder and the next includes drafts of minutes, notes and correspondence, including correspondence concerning York & Sawyer.
  - Building Committee. General (2 of 2), 1904 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Includes correspondence between Committee Secretary Sydney Carney and Committee Chair Samuel Hoffman; see also NYHS-RG 1, Series IV. Official Papers for other documents concerning the Carney and Hoffman exchange.
  - Trustees of the New Building. General (1 of 3), 1904-1905 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    This folder and the next two includes drafts of minutes, notes and correspondence.
  - Trustees of the New Building. General (2 of 3), 1906 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Trustees of the New Building. General (3 of 3), 1907-1908 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Letterpress Book, 1904, 1906 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    This is a letterpress book started by Clarence Storm in 1904 for the Building Committee, when he became secretary of that committee. It includes only 3 outgoing letters bound in the book (all to York & Sawyer), and two others loose at the front of the book.
  - Howells & Stokes. Competitive Design for the N-YHS's Building, 1904 (Box OS-1, Folder 17)
    Includes the design proposed by architects Howells & Stokes as published in American Architect and Architecture Vol. 84, June 4, 1904. This published plate appears to have been purchased by N-YHS for the Print Room collection. The number 2011.9 is noted on the back. It was moved to the institutional archive in 2016.
  - Henry Dexter Donation (1 of 8), 1904-1908 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Henry Dexter Donation (2 of 8), 1905-1908 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Henry Dexter Donation (3 of 8), 1905-1906 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Henry Dexter Donation (4 of 8), 1906-1907 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Henry Dexter Donation (5 of 8), 1908 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Henry Dexter Donation (6 of 8), 1906? (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Henry Dexter Donation (7 of 8). Van Norden Trust Co. Account Books and Cancelled Checks, 1905-1906, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Also includes the financial report for Van Norden Trust Company as of January 1, 1908.
  - Henry Dexter Donation (8 of 8). Second National Bank Account Books and Cancelled Checks, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (1 of 12), 1901-1902 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (2 of 12), 1903 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Includes specifications for the work, dated November 19, 1903. Oversize blueprint of retaining wall, enclosed by York & Sawyer with their letter of February 19, 1903, was removed to an oversize container; see folder 12 of 12 below.
  - York & Sawyer Matters (3 of 12), 1904 January-September (Box 9, Folder 2)
    A former label indicating that some of the documents in this series were from the Hoffman papers, received April 1943, is in this folder.
  - York & Sawyer Matters (4 of 12), 1904 October 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Includes specifications as of October 1, 1904.
  - York & Sawyer Matters (5 of 12), 1904 October-December (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (6 of 12), 1905 January-March (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (7 of 12), 1905 April-December (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Includes an addenda to the specifications, dated July 27, 1905.
  - York & Sawyer Matters (8 of 12), 1906 January-May (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (9 of 12), 1906 June-December (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (10 of 12), 1907 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (11 of 12), 1908, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - York & Sawyer Matters (12 of 12), [1903] (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 18)
    Includes oversize material removed from above folder 2 of 12: blueprint of retaining wall on rear property.
  - York & Sawyer. Weekly Reports of Work Done at Site, 1904 December-1907 February (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Contractor Bids, Circulars, and Offers (1 of 3), 1901-1902 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Contractor Bids, Circulars, and Offers (2 of 3), 1903-1904 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Contractor Bids, Circulars, and Offers (3 of 3), 1905-1909 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Includes Morgan & Brothers bid for moving collections from the 2nd Avenue site to Central Park West.
  - John F. O'Rourke Contract and Correspondence, 1902-1903 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Heating Plant System, 1902, 1905, 1907 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Library Bureau Contract and Correspondence (1 of 2), 1906, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Blueprints were removed to an oversize container; see the next folder.
  - Library Bureau Contract and Correspondence (2 of 2), 1909-1910 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 5)
    Includes 5 oversize blueprints of museum cases from the Library Bureau.
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (1 of 9), 1904-1906 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    This folder and the next include signed contracts and correspondence, bids, and records of payments to various contractors. The Andrew J. Robinson Company and its sub-contractors are well-represented here. There is also some correspondence with York & Sawyer. Several documents relate to the arrangements agreed upon between N-YHS and Henry Dexter. The contents of the folders appear to have come entirely or in substantial part from the papers of Samuel V. Hoffman.
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (2 of 9), 1903-1904 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Includes a signed contract, and drafts, with the Andrew J. Robinson Co.
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (3 of 9), 1904 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Includes contract between the Andrew J. Robinson Co. and the American Bonding Co.
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (4 of 9), 1905 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Includes signed contracts with the Andrew J. Robinson Co.
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (5 of 9), 1905 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Includes contracts between Andrew J. Robinson Co. and its sub-contractors: Baker, Smith & Co (heating & ventilating), J.B. & J.M. Cornell Co. (iron work), McWilliam Brothers (granite setting), Peet, McAnerney & Powers (electric), and R. Guastavino Co. (tile arches).
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (6 of 9), 1906, 1908-1909 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Includes contracts of 1906 between Andrew J. Robinson Co. and its sub-contractors: James Morrison, Jr. (plastering), Library Bureau (book stacks, lift and elevator), P. & F. Corbin (hardware), Ronald Taylor (concrete), Traitel Marble Co. (marble work for main staircase), and Voightmann & Co (copper windows). Includes the contract of 1908 between Robinson Co and Henry Dexter for completion of the Museum Room.
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (7 of 9), 1904-1907 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (8 of 9), 1902, 1904-1905 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    This folder and the next primarily includes correspondence between the Andrew J. Robinson Company and Samuel V. Hoffman.
  - Contracts and Other Project Records (9 of 9), 1906-1908 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Utilities Certifications, 1907, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    Includes certifications from the New York Board of Fire Underwriters and the Department of Water Supply, Gas and Electricity.
  - Cornerstone Ceremony (1 of 3), 1903 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    Includes the announcement to newspaper editors of the event; sample invitations, including one directed to Daniel Parish, Jr.; a photograph album of the event with six images; a list of objects in the cornerstone (fragmented); and correspondence, principally with York & Sawyer concerning arrangements.
  - Cornerstone Ceremony (2 of 3), 1903 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 10)
    Includes one oversize blueprint of the grandstand for the ceremony and a plan showing the location of the cornerstone, both from York & Sawyer.
  - Cornerstone Ceremony (3 of 3), 1903 (Box 11, Folder -)
    Includes artifacts related to the event including ribbons, pins, and other items.
  - Civil Engineer Surveys, 1901-1902 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 8)
    Includes four drawings (whiteprints) of surveys of the Central Park West site conducted by civil engineer and city surveyor Peter E. Nostrand.
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1902 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 16)
    Includes three drawings (whiteprints): transverse (#5), Central Park West elevation (#6), and 77th Street elevation (#8).
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1902 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 15)
    Includes 17 drawings (whiteprints) concerning floor plans, foundation, framing, and others: drawings #1, #2, #3, #4, #7 (rear elevation), #10, #14, #15, #16, #17, #18, #19, #20, #21, #22 (retaining wall at rear property line), #23, and #24.
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1902 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 14)
    Includes three reproductions of plans related to foundation piers and beams: drawings #15, 16, and 17. The plans were stamped by the New York City Bureau of Buildings as received on November 3, 1902.
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1903-1904 (Roll -, Folder -)
    Includes several conserved, rolled linens. The documents were not unrolled during processing so the specific plans included are undescribed.
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1904 (Drawer 9B-B1, Folder 4)
    Includes two drawings (blueprints): framing plan of 1st floor (#46) and framing plan of 2nd floor (#47).
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1904 (Drawer 9B-B1, Folder 2)
    Includes one drawing (blueprint) of transverse section, drawing #30.
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1904 (Drawer 9B-B1, Folder 3)
    Includes one drawing (blueprint) of the roof plan. Title box partially missing; plan number unknown.
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, [1904] (Drawer 9B-B1, Folder 1)
    Includes three drawings (blueprints): framing plan of 3rd floor (#missing; dated June 3), framing plan of roof (#missing; dated June 3); and 77th Street elevation (number missing; date missing).
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1904-1905 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 11)
    Includes two drawings (whiteprints): section through entrance (#60, 1904) and plumbing section (#102, 1905).
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1904-1905, undated (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 17)
    Includes three drawings (whiteprints): front elevation (#51, rev, 1904), library stack room (#130; 1905), and granite work (#58, undated).
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1904, 1906 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 12)
    Includes five drawings (blueprints): #51 (front elevation), #52 (section of entrance, 2 copies), #54 (granite), and #201 (main stairway, 1906).
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, [1904] (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 1)
    Includes a watercolor (?) of the proposed Central Park West building, signed by York & Sawyer, and a black and white reproduction of the original.
  - York & Sawyer Drawings, 1907 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 13)
    Includes 13 drawings (blueprints) concerning library: drawings #239, #251, #252 (stairs), #254, #255, #256, #257, #258, #259 (rev), #260, #265, #273, and #274.
  - [York & Sawyer] Drawings, 1907 (Drawer 9B-B1, Folder 5)
    Includes one drawing (blueprint) of cross-section of north and south end (#269).
  - {York & Sawyer?] Drawing, undated (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 9)
    Includes one drawing of the floor design for the 77th Street entrance.
  - Library Bureau Drawings, 1906 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 6)
    Includes eight drawings (blueprints) of the book stack room, book lift and steel shelving. With the possible exception of one drawing, all appear to be from the Library Bureau, though not all are identified as such.
  - Library Bureau Drawings, 1908 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 7)
    Includes 23 drawings (blueprints) of library cases, chairs, desk, and other furniture, and of the library floor plan.
  - Nygren, Tenney & Ohmes Drawings (1 of 2), 1915 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 19)
    Includes a specification report and three associated plans from consulting engineers for additions and alterations to the ventilating apparatus for the N-YHS auditorium and library.
  - Nygren, Tenney & Ohmes Drawings (2 of 2), 1915 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 20)
    Includes three linens with plans for the ventilating work.
  - Snead & Co. Iron Works and Library Bureau Drawings, 1917-1918, undated (Drawer 9B-B1, Folder 6)
    Includes six drawings (blueprints) of details of exhibition and museum cases by Snead & Co. There is also one undated drawing, possibly from Snead, of a cast iron leg. Also includes two drawings (blueprints) by Library Bureau of manuscript cases (1918) and the stack layout (undated).
- Series IV. Central Park West Construction: Expansion, 1925-1946; 68.48 Linear feet
  The series is organized in four subseries:
  A. General Project Documents
  B. Construction Management Documents
  C. Plans and Drawings
  D. Post-Construction Plans
  The series includes documents concerning the expansion of the Central Park West building in 1937-1938. This expansion primarily involved the addition of wings to the north and south sides and a fifteen floor book stack to the rear of the existing building. The series includes well over 1200 blueprints and other formats of plans created by architects Walker & GIllette, construction contractor Turner Construction Company, and various subcontractors for the project, though many of the plans are represented with multiple copies or revised versions. The series also includes construction specifications, progress reports, meeting summaries, correspondence among the principals, contracts, detailed supporting documentation from Turner Construction and their sub-contractors for work done and materials used, and payment records related to the support documentation. There are a small number of photographs of the construction site.
  In addition to the 1937-1938 records, the series includes a small number of documents from the 1920s. These include York & Sawyer's 1925 proposed expansion plans, related correspondence, documents related to the 1925 acquisition of property from Sarah Straus on West 76th Street, and a certified copy of a 1926 deed conveying property on West 77th Street from John A. and Elsa A. Weekes to N-YHS. There are also a small number of plans dating from the 1940s, shortly after the 1937-1938 expansion, including preliminary plans drawn by architect Philip N. Youtz in 1945-1946 for a further expansion of the building to encompass an Education Building.
  - Subseries IV.A. General Project Documents, 1925-1926, 1935-1939; 3.96 Linear feet in 9.5 document boxes
    The subseries is arranged topically. The subseries begins with materials that provide an overview of the project, including Building Committee minutes, general correspondence, and minutes of the regular project meetings led by Walker & Gillette. These files are followed by correspondence of a more specific nature, including that with the architects, Walker & Gillette, and the general contractor, Turner Construction Co. These files are followed by the multiple sets of specifications, the sub-contractor files, Turner's monthly payment applications with supporting documents, and packing lists.
    The General Project Documents subseries includes files that appear, for the most part, to have been maintained by N-YHS Director Alexander J. Wall during the construction. The subseries includes minutes and general correspondence of the Building Committee overseeing the project, architect Walker & Gillette's summaries of the regular construction status meetings they led, and correspondence with Walker & Gillette, general contractor Turner Construction Company, and other architects and contractors bidding for work. Among the architects bidding for the work, but not winning, was York & Sawyer, the architectural firm that had designed the central portion of the Central Park West building and that had offered designs for an expansion in the 1920s and in 1935; the subseries holds correspondence with that firm. The subseries holds a set of files concerning the various project sub-contractors and providers of materials; these include copies of the contracts between Turner and the sub-contractors and other documents.
    The subseries holds three sets of project specifications. There appears to be substantial overlap in the three sets, but also some differences among them in their level of completeness and the documents they include. One difference appears to be in how the specifications were originally filed, and perhaps whose files the specifications came from. One set, detailed in the container list, is alphabetical by the work to be done. A second set was numbered, though that is also roughly alphabetical. The third set is bound together.
    The subseries includes the monthly payment applications made by Turner Construction. These packets include detailed back-up including hours worked and materials used on the job, along with sub-contractor billings. There are also the detailed packing lists used in shipping the collection to offsite storage during the project.
    The date range of the subseries begins in 1925-1926. This early date relates to documents concerning property acquisitions along West 76th and 77th streets, from Sarah Straus and John A. Weekes and Elsa A. Weekes, respectively.
    - Building Committee Minutes (1 of 2), 1935-1936 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Building Committee Minutes (2 of 2), 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Building Committee Correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Primarily includes copies of Alexander Wall's outgoing correspondence to the Building Committee and its counsel. Includes the recommendation to hire Garrett H. Winter as the project's clerk of the works.
    - Project Meeting Minutes (1 of 2), 1936-1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      This folder and the next include the reports prepared by Walker & Gillette of the regular meetings of the project principals. In addition to Walker & Gillette, attendees typically included representatives from N-YHS (usually just Alexander J. Wall, though George Zabriskie or others attended on occasion), Turner Construction, and clerk of the works, Garrett Winter. Some meetings included representatives of particular sub-contractors.
    - Project Meeting Minutes (2 of 2), 1938 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - West 76th and 77th Street Property Matters, 1925-1926, 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Includes various documents related to property matters, including easements and conveyances, especially concerning numbers 7 through 13 on West 76th. Includes certified copies of the 1925 indenture for the sale by Sarah Strauss of 5 W. 76th and the 1926 indenture for the sale by John A. Weekes and Elsa A. Weekes of property at West 77th St.
    - Project Miscellaneous Documents, 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Includes various general documents related to the project: project budgets and cost estimates; notes on N-YHS Executive Committee resolutions; and a list of rooms that have buzzers, clocks, telephones, and push-buttons.
    - Bids of Architects, 1925, 1935-1936 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Primarily includes correspondence with York & Sawyer concerning the possibility of them doing the architectural work for the expansion; this includes photostats of N-YHS's 1925 correspondence concerning the plans drawn at that time by York & Sawyer. Includes John Hill Morgan's resignation from the Executive Committee and N-YHS related to the expansion plans. Includes correspondence with Walker & Gillette offering them the contract.
    - Bids of Contractors (1 of 2), 1936, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      This folder includes Turner Construction Company's material concerning their bid for the N-YHS construction. Turner's documents include photographs of buildings they recently constructed: Hotel Lexington (New York), New Jersey Bell Telephone Comany (Newark), Fidelity Mutual Life Insurance Company (Philadelphia), Girard College Library and Chapel (Philadelphia), Pennsylvania Hospital (Philadelphia), Provident Mutual Life Insurance Company (Philadelphia), The Breakers Hotel (Palm Beach, Fla.), Massachusetts Mutal Life Insurance Company (Springfield), and Acacia Mutual Life Insurance Company (Washington, DC).
    - Bids of Contractors (2 of 2), 1936 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Includes proposals from, most substantively, John Lowry, Inc., A.L. Hartridge Company, and The Whitney Company. The folder also includes a summary of some of the bids received.
    - Correspondence with Walker & Gillette (1 of 3), 1936 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Includes the agreement between N-YHS and Walker & Gillette.
    - Correspondence with Walker & Gillette (2 of 3), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with Walker & Gillette (3 of 3), 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with Turner Construction Co. (1 of 2), 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Turner Construction Co. (2 of 2), 1938-1939 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Includes Turner's "Work Completed in the One Year 1937" which lists and depicts as a "city" all of Turner's projects; the N-YHS building is included in the image.
    - Correspondence with Gaines, Silvey & Nichols (Insurance), 1936-1938 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Book Stacks, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Bronze Work, Architectural, Miscellaneous Iron, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Carpenter Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Electric Lighting Fixtures, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Electric Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Elevators, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Fireproof Floor, Roof Construction and Cinder Fill & Cement Finish Floors, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Floor Coverings, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Glass & Glazing, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Glass Block, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Granite, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Hardware, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Heating, Ventilating & Air Conditioning, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Hollow Metal & Kalamein Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Marble Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Mason Materials, Concrete & Cement Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Metal Lathing & Furring, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Metal Windows, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Mosaic Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Painting, 1937-1938 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Pile Foundation, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Plastering, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Plumbing, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Roofing & Sheet Metal Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Skeleton, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Structural Steel, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Terrazzo Work, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Tile, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Specifications (Set 1-Alphabetical). Wood Floors, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 29)